Inventory of the Middletown Manuscripts Collection, 1668 - 1937
Middletown Manuscripts Collection, 1668 - 1937
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
1000-171
0.75
2
The Middletown Manuscripts Collection is an intentionally created collection of disparate manuscripts related to the history of Middletown, Connecticut.
The majority of this collection is 18th- and 19th-century documents from around the Middletown, Connecticut area, with some documents from the 17th- and 20th-centuries.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Acquired from multiple sources prior to 1980.
Historical Note
The Middletown Manuscripts Collection is an intentionally created collection of disparate manuscripts related to the history of Middletown, Connecticut.
Collection Overview
The majority of this collection is 18th- and 19th-century documents from around the Middletown area, with some documents from the 17th- and 20th-centuries. Most of the documents contained in this collection are legal documents, such as deeds, petitions, issued tickets, bills, etc. There are documents about the railroad in Middletown, including the documents about the building process of the extension through Middletown. The shipping records in the collection include some information about the ships themselves, as well as some information about where they were coming from and who was part of the crew. There is a folder of financial information belonging to the Addis family, which is primarily a collection of bills for Miss Addis and all the purchases she made. Another folder has financial information related to the Doane family. There are two bound books in the collection. The first has very little written in it, but it includes some correspondence between father and son in the de Zeng family about financial issues. The second bound book is a detailed journal kept by Charles H. Neff about the discovery of Indian relics and old Indian settlements in and around the Middletown area.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Middletown (Conn.)--History.; Middlesex County (Conn.)--History.; Shipping--Connecticut River.; Wilcox, Crittenden & Co.--History.; Railroad companies--United States.; Paper money--United States.; Addis family.; De Zeng family.; Neff, Charles H.; Indians of North America--Material culture--Connecticut.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Wilcox, Crittenden & Co, Inc. Data
    History and stories of the first grist mill in Middlesex County.
    - The early beginnings of the company, the first grist mill in Middlesex county, the oldest manufacturers of marine hardware in America, William Walter Wilcox, President, June 10, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - A brief history of the First Successful Application in the United States of America in the Hot Dip Process of Galvanizing, William Walter Wilcox, President, June 14, 1937 (Folder 1)
    - Yankee Ingenuity by Frank Wyman, Connecticut Yachtsman magazine, August 28, 1937 (Folder 1)
    - It's a long, long way to anywhere, when there's no sign post to guide you, 1914 (Folder 1)
      The story of the old mill; Old Mill in the Lives of Our Forefathers; The Highway that runs by the Mill; Some Who Passed on the Old Road; Grinding the Old Stand; Inspecting Invited
  - Mansion-House Bills, E.W. Newton, Middletown, CT
    - Mr. L. L. Panosc (Box 1, Folder 2)
      To E. W. Newton, Dr., for Board from Hon. A.H. Everett on August 2, 1898 for $3.73.
    - Mr. Deming (Folder 2)
      To E. W. Newton, Dr., for 3 meals and housekeeping on October 14, 1894 for $1.50.
  - School Association of the County of Middlesex
    - Constitution of the School Association of the County of Middlesex, 1799 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      18 articles. Accepted unanimously, Thaddeus Nichols, Secretary, Middletown, CT, February 7, 1799
  - Legal Documents: Deeds, Petitions, Grants
    - John Wilcox of Guilford, May 12, 1737 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      For the sum of 45 pounds and 14 shillings to Deliverance Warner and Mary Gaylord, Wilcox received 7 1/2 acres and 20 rods of land. Signed, sealed, delivered in the presence of Samuel Craval.
    - Mary Gaylord of Middletown, December 27, 1738 (Folder 4)
      All common and undivided land of the East side of the River in South Middletown and gift of the heirs to her brother Deliverance Warner. Witnessed by Joseph Lockwell and Wm. Rockwell.
    - Abigail Cooper of Middletown, February 2, 1747 (Folder 4)
      For 21 pounds and 5 shillings from John Cooper (her son) for 4 acres and 39 rods on the East side of the Connecticut River.
    - Stephen Bishop of Middletown, April 20, 1747 (Folder 4)
      For 300 pounds from William Southmayo (?) for 7 acres on the West side of the Connecticut River.
    - George Romney of Middletown, June 26, 1751 (Folder 4)
      For 350 pounds from John Cooper for 6 acres on the East side of the Connecticut River. Witnessed by Seth Rockwell and Timothy Cornwall.
    - February 2, 1756 death certificate (Folder 4)
      Javez Hamlin, Esq. To Thomas Bliss, whereas Daniel Bliss deceased.
    - George Stillman, August 26, 1765 (Folder 4)
      For 6 pounds and 10 shillings form Sylvanus Waterman and Seth Knowles for 2 ½ acres on the East side of the Connecticut River. Witnessed by Joseph White and Isaac Waterman. 1 copy for 18 pounds; 1 copy for 7 pounds and 10 shillings; and 1 copy for 43 pounds and 1 shilling.
    - Jacob Whitmore, December 23, 1766 (Folder 4)
      250 pounds from Cap. Sam Russell for 3/4 acre.
    - Bezaleel Latimer and Nancy Latimer, November 20, 1797 (Folder 4)
      For 130 pounds from Justus Riley of Wethersfield for 26 acres and 26 rods.
    - Nathaniel Merriam, April 8, 1799 (Folder 4)
      For $300 from Benjamin Merriam for 16 acres and 29 rods in Wallingford. Witnessed by Sam Woodruff and J. Atwater.
    - Thomas and Rhoda Griswold, James and Mary Smith, October 26, 1803 (Folder 4)
      For $1 from Samuel Tudor of East Windsor for land 3 miles in length and 33 rods in width in East Windsor.
    - To the Honorable Superior Court next to be holden, by special resolve of the Legislature of the State of Connecticut, at Middletown, within and for the county of Middlesex, on the fourth Tuesday in August, A.D. 1829 (Folder 4)
      A list of debts and to whom they are owed for an unknown person, by his attorneys, Storrs and Mather, dated July 13, 1829. With a summon to those owed money to the court by judge of the superior court, Stephen T. Hosmer.
    - William Boardman, September 18, 1877 (Folder 4)
      New Haven, Middletown, and Willimantic Railroad Company. Signed William Boardman.
    - Miller document
      - Goodman Miller, January 21, 1661 (Folder 4)
        The town granted him 10 acres.
      - Thomas Miller, May 29, 1667 (Folder 4)
        The town accepted Thomas Miller's gift of a highway.
      - Thomas Miller, November 26, 1668 (Folder 4)
        The town grants him the liberty of the river above the mill to dig and dam for preserving water.
      - Thomas Miller, December 19, 1677 (Folder 4)
        The town exchanges a piece of land, rod for rod, to enlarge the highway to the mill.
      - Goodman Miller, February 12, 1679 or 1680 (Folder 4)
        The town granted to exchange a parcel of land by the mill.
      - Thomas Miller, February 1, 1710 or 1711 (Folder 4)
        The town granted him 1 1/2 acres near the mill.
  - Shipping, 18th century
    Bills for shipping, financial notes, and salary notes of ships traveling in and out of Middletown.
    - August 2, 1796, Middletown (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Benjamin Williams to Dr. William Stam
    - June 5, 1759, Middletown (Folder 5)
      Sugar sales, a bargain for a friend. Letter from Comfort Sage to Mr. Sam Cotton.
    - August 2, 1796, New London (Folder 5)
      To Capt. Williams from John Andrews (for $9) and Stephen Northlus (for $50).
    - May 3, 1796, Middletown (Folder 5)
      To William Jepson for 15 nights on Sloop Scrub's 2nd voyage.
    - May 2, 1796, Middletown (Folder 5)
      To John Williams.
    - May 2, 1796, Middletown (Folder 5)
      To William Scovel.
    - April 22, 1796 (Folder 5)
      Capt. Benjamin Williams to John Nolls.
    - April 30, 1796 (Folder 5)
      To John Harris.
    - April 21, 1796 (Folder 5)
      John Williams Master. Boat of Ebenezer Sage, captain.
    - April 20, 1796 (Folder 5)
      Capt. John Williams to George Starrs.
    - April 29, 1796 (Folder 5)
      To Israel Driggs from Capt. Benjamin Williams.
    - August 10, 1796, Middletown (Folder 5)
      Capt. Benjamin Williams to John Daniels, James Daniels, John Williams, B. Williams, Josiah Scifile, Simon Taylor for wages. List of the ship's costs, including wages totaling $378.14.
  - Shipping, 19th century
    Tickets for trips on ships and boats, legal documents in regard to shipping and seamen.
    - Connecticut River Valley Steam-Boat ticket, January 20, 1831 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      20 miles travel, Windsor, JW Hubbard.
    - Steam Boat Oliver Ellsworth, September 1, 1829 (Folder 6)
      Ticket entitles Richard Hubbard 1 passage between Middletown and Hartford.
    - November 8, 1820 (Folder 6)
      Shipping from Middletown to New York, names illegible.
    - Middletown Insurance Company, December 13, 1803 (Folder 6)
      William C. Hall, Middletown to Charlston, South Carolina. Jason Goodwin, master of the voyage. Amount insured: $1700. Signed by Benjamin Williams and A. Miller, secretary.
    - An Act for the Government and Regulation of Seamen on the Merchants Service, July 20, 1790 (document approved) (Folder 6)
      Signed in Middletown August 6, 1801.
    - Extract of an Act for the Relief and Protection of American Seaman (Folder 6)
      Report and manifest of the cargo laden on board of the Schooner F.H.C. where of Chancy Barnard is master, taken on board at the port of St. Croix bound for the port of Middletown, May 20, 1804. List of packages and contents.
    - An Act for the Government and Regulation of Seamen in the Merchant Service (Folder 6)
      Signed January 16, 1806 by James Seymour, Edward Dodge, James Barnard. Bound for the port of Barbados and Back, 1805. Chancy Barnard, master; Edward Dodge, mate; James Barnard, seaman; James C., seaman; David S., seaman; Thomas Curtis, seaman; Silas Stewart, cook; and James Seymour, cook. Wages totaling $271.98.
  - Railroads: Receipts and Notices
    Receipts and notices of the building and expansion of the railroad in and around Middletown.
    - Ticket issued by New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company, February 13, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      1 first class passage to Washington, D.C. from Philadelphia.
    - July 6, 1848, Middletown (Folder 7)
      Received from William G. Buell of Chatham sum of $2.50, the 2nd installment on 5 shares of Capital Stock in the New York & Boston Railroad Company. Signed Stephen Taylor, Treasurer.
    - New York & Boston Railroad Notice, June 29, 1848 (Folder 7)
      Locations for railroad in Connecticut. Signed H. Closson.
    - July 22, 1858 (Folder 7)
      To Rachel Penny and Charles R. Alsop of Middletown, executors and trustees under the last will and testament of George Penny.
    - The Middletown Extension Railroad Company (Folder 7)
      Letter to those who may have had objections to the proposed location of the railroad: Description of where the railroad will go with a promise of a meeting with the general railroad commissions on August 25, 1858 in Middletown for the people to object.
    - August 25, 1849 (Folder 7)
      Letter to those who may have had objections to the proposed location of the railroad: from the Middletown Railroad Company to Berlin, Middletown, some individuals out of the area and some corporations stating where they plan to build the railroad. Signed Ebenezer White.
    - July 2, 1849 (Folder 7)
      Letter to those who may have had objections to the proposed location of the railroad: from Middletown Railroad Company to Berlin, Middletown, some individuals out of the area, and some corporations stating where they plan to build the railroad. Signed William M. Ward.
  - Paper money, stampless cover, etc.
    Bank promises of payment.
    - March 10, 1785 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      The State of Connecticut owes 11 pounds and 14 shillings to Comfort Sage and promises to pay by March 10, 1788 with an interest of 6% per year. Signed I. Lawrence, treasurer.
    - June 1, 1782 (Folder 8)
      Connecticut owes Abigail Hubbard 19 pounds and 10 shillings to be paid by June 1, 1786 with lawful interest. Signed I. Lawrence, treasurer.
    - February 1, 1781 (Folder 8)
      Connecticut owes Abraham Doolittle 10 pounds and 17 shillings to be paid on or before the end of the year with 6% interest per year. Signed I. Lawrence, treasurer.
    - Paper Money
      - February 10, 1815, Middletown Bank (Folder 8)
        20 cent notice. Signed by cashier and N. Hubbard, president.
      - May 1, 1819, Middletown Bank (Folder 8)
        Promise to pay I. Mason $10. Signed by cashier and N. Hubbard, president.
      - February 1, 1816, Middletown Bank (Folder 8)
        3 cent note. Signed by cahier and N. Hubbard, president.
      - November 7, 1856, Middletown Bank (Folder 8)
        $3. Signed by F.G. Gleason, cashier, and Watkinson, president.
      - May 1, 1819, Middletown Bank (Folder 8)
        Promise to pay J. West $10. Signed by cashier and Nathan Hubbard, President.
    - Stampless cover: November 29, Middletown (Folder 8)
      A stampless cover was an envelope that was posted before the time when the use of postage stamps became mandatory for sending mail (January 1, 1856). 3 cents paid. Miss Frances Baker, Port Byron, NY. Envelope with no letter.
    - Naboth Lewis of Middletown has manufactured 2 ½ pounds of silk from worms of his own raising the summer past, May 9, 1791 (Folder 8)
      Registered in the front office, September 29, 1791 for 6 shillings and 8 pence. Signed Dodd and Joshua Stow.
  - Miscellaneous
    - January 23, 1816 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Humphrey Pratt of Saybrook has paid the duty of $1, for the year, to end of the 31st day of December next, for a two wheel carriage owned by him and the harness used. Signed L. Stow, collector of the Revenue for the 6th collection district of Connecticut.
    - January 23, 1816 (Folder 9)
      A bound book of financial information for the Ecclesiastical Society of Middletown, payable by November 1, 1799.
    - June 23, 1813 (Folder 9)
      I, William M.H., one of the bishops of the Methodist Episcopal Church have set this day apart Edward Hyde for the office of an elder in the Methodist Episcopal Church (a recommendation).
    - Appointment certificate of Peter Comstock, Esq. to the position of Post-Master in the office of River Head in the county of New London, January 1816 (Folder 9)
      Return J, Megis, Junior Post-Master General of the United States of America. Signed January 1816 by R.J. Megis and Stephen Gray, clerk.
    - June 13, 1892 (Folder 9)
      To R.E. Thompson from J.S. Stewart, Dr., printer and bookbinder. Bill for 1000 YMCA notes.
    - July 1, 1892 (Folder 9)
      Bill to Mr. R.W. Raymond from Lucius R. Hazen, wholesale and retail bookseller, stationer and news dealer, for a cash box.
    - April 12, 1894 (Folder 9)
      Bill to Wesleyan YMCA building from J.S. Stewart for 400 receipts.
  - Addis Family
    Bills and other financial documents.
    - January 23, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Be it known that the Miner Cemetery Association of Middletown in considerations of $10 received from William H. Addis for lot #102. Signed by Joel M. Clark, justice of the peace, Herbert Smith, James Smith, president, and Julius S. Bacon, secretary.
    - Miner Cemetery Association, March 30, 1870 (Folder 10)
      William H. Addis is entitled to 1 share of the capital stock of the Miners Cemetery Association. Signed James Smith, president.
    - July 1, 1897 (Folder 10)
      F. Brewer & Co., Dry Goods Exclusively. Bill for Miss Addis.
    - August 9, 1897 (Folder 10)
      F. Brewer & Co. Bill for Miss Addis.
    - December 1, 1897 (Folder 10)
    - January 1, 1898 (Folder 10)
    - March 5, 1898 (Folder 10)
    - April 1, 1898 (Folder 10)
    - July 1, 1898 (Folder 10)
    - September 20, 1898 (Folder 10)
    - January 2, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - April 22, 1899 (Folder 10)
      F. Brewer & Co. received $15 from Miss Addis.
    - June 8, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - July 1, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - October 2, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - January 1, 1900 (Folder 10)
    - February 3, 1900 (Folder 10)
      F. Brewer & Co. received $3 from Miss Addis.
    - April 2, 1900 (Folder 10)
    - January 29, 1898 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce, Dry Goods, Carpets and Furniture. Received $3.98 from Miss Addis.
    - July 24, 1900 (Folder 10)
    - January 3, 1898 (Folder 10)
      James H. Bunce. Bill for Miss Addis.
    - September 20, 1898 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce received $1 from Miss Addis.
    - September 24, 1898 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce bill for $1.75 for Miss Addis.
    - November 1, 1898 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce bill for $2.50 for Miss Addis.
    - January 3, 1899 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce bill.
    - June 3, 1899 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce received $3.43.
    - July 1, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - November 2, 1899 (Folder 10)
      J.H. Bunce received $3.75.
    - January 7, 1899 (Folder 10)
      Caulkins & Post, Carpets, Draperies, Furniture, etc. Received $4.
    - September 1, 1899 (Folder 10)
      Caulkins & Post bill.
    - November 27, 1899 (Folder 10)
      Caulkins & Post received $7.05.
    - December 6 (Folder 10)
      Bill from J.A. Broatch, Bookseller, Stationer and Newsdealer.
    - July 25, 1899 (Folder 10)
      Bill from J.A. Broatch.
    - December 31, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - January 9, 1899 (Folder 10)
      Bill from Buell & Blatchley, Druggists.
    - July 1, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - October 10, 1899 (Folder 10)
    - December 31, 1898 (Folder 10)
      Bill from J. McCarthy, Interior and Exterior Decorating.
    - February 2 1898 (Folder 10)
      Bill from L. Bailey, MD.
    - February 24, 1890 (Folder 10)
      Bill from The Singer Manufacturing Co.
    - May 23, 1894 (Folder 10)
      L.R. Hazen received $3.
    - December 31, 1897 (Folder 10)
      L.R. Hazen received $1.
    - January 11, 1898 (Folder 10)
      L.R. Hazen received $2.
    - April 29, 1899 (Folder 10)
      DeKraus received $2.25.
    - August 14, 1899 (Folder 10)
      J.F. Parker received $45.
    - Russell Free Library War Relics Collections received objects from Capt. W.H. Addis (Folder 10)
    - Knitting pattern for Jenny Jacket (Folder 10)
  - Doane family
    - November 14, 1842 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Samuel Miller of Saybrook for the consideration of $140 received from Josiah Doane of Saybrook for about 1 acre and 2 rods of land. Signed by Samuel Miller, John L. Whittelsey, M.A. Whittelsey.
    - June 24, 1842 (Folder 11)
      Richard Jones of New York received $13.75 from Josiah A. Doane of Saybrook for 8 acres and 34 rods of land. Signed by R.S. Jones, James C. Holmes, Edmund Porter.
    - March 7, 1871 (Folder 11)
      Asa Kirtland Jr. of Saybrook sells Josiah A. Doane a piece of land in the ferry district of Saybrook of about 10 acres from $225. Signed by Asa Kirtland, Henry Kirtland (justice of the peace), Jane M.B..
    - April 8, 1871 (Folder 11)
      Jeanette Bushnell of Old Saybrook sold Josiah A. Doane 4 acres of Old Saybrook for $150. Signed Henry Hart, Jeannette Bushnell, Mary Hart.
    - June 9, 1874 (Folder 11)
      Ms. Caroline Jones and Ms. Augusta Campbell of New York, J. Edmund Jones of Chester, Connecticut, Henry Jones of Meriden, Ellen Whitney of Springfield, Massachusetts sold Josiah A. Doane 1 acre for $200.
    - September 18, 1883 (Folder 11)
      Eunice A. Addis, wife of Wm. Addis, sold Josiah A. Doane 4 acres for $500. Signed by Eunice A. Addis, Ozias H. Kirtland, Grace Kirtland.
    - February 11, 1890 (Folder 11)
      Eunice and William Addis sold Josiah Doane 12 acres for $500.
    - March 29, 1894 (Folder 11)
      Amanda A. Doane of Colchester sold William R. Havens a piece of land in Old Saybrook. Signed by O.H. Kirtland, Ann Amanda Doane, Caroline Havens.
    - March 29, 1894 (Folder 11)
      William R. Havens of Old Saybrook sold Frank A. Doane of Colchester about 1 acre for $45. Signed by William R. Havens, C. Havens, O.H. Kirtland.
    - July 3, 1894 (Folder 11)
      Letter from O.H. Kirtland to Mrs. Doane explaining the partially filled out deed.
    - July 10, 1894 (Folder 11)
      Ann Amanda Doane sold Eunice A. Addis 14 acres and 4 acres in Old Saybrook for $300.
    - September 25, 1874 (Folder 11)
      Promise to pay the Essex Savings Bank $250 with 7% interest. Signed by Josiah A. Doane.
    - March 25, 1884 (Folder 11)
      Essex Savings Bank received $250 from Josiah A. Doane.
    - July 6, 1882 (Folder 11)
      J.A. Doane to F.A Doane: List of money borrowed. Payment received to the satisfaction of F.A. Doane October 4, 1882.
    - June 5, 1884 (Folder 11)
      Josiah A. Doane last will and testament. Notarized
    - June 5, 1884 (Folder 11)
      Josiah A Doane last will and testament. Draft.
    - March 7, 1893 (Folder 11)
      Letter to Mrs. Doane from Henry H. (2 pages)
    - March 29, 1893 (Folder 11)
      Letter to Mrs. Doane from John N. Clark.
    - April 10, 1894 (Folder 11)
      Bill from C.D. Burnham & Son, Monumental Works to Mrs. Amanda A. Doane for a headstone.
    - April 10, 1893 (Folder 11)
      Envelope addressed to Mrs. Josiah A. Doane from Old Saybrook.
    - December 9, 1895 (Folder 11)
      Bill for Mrs. Doane's Estate from M.W. Robinson, MD.
    - December 10, 1895 (Folder 11)
      Bill to Estate of Amanda A. Doane from Geo. W. Walker, Proprietor of Livery and Feed.
    - December 13, 1895 (Folder 11)
      Check for $12.50 to M.W. Robinson.
    - December 13, 1895 (Folder 11)
      Check for $60 to P.A. Dawley & Son.
  - Richard L. de Zeng correspondence and bills, 1872-1873 (Box 1)
    1 bound volume. Richard L. de Zeng owned the house on High Street later occupied by the Epsilon Gamma Chapter of the Sigma Nu Fraternity.
    - Late bills (for $500)
    - Letter to son about paying the late bills/finances
    - Business letter to son
    - Financial correspondence between father and son
  - Indian Localities around Portland, Connecticut and Lists of Indian Relics Collected in that Vicinity by Charles H. Neff (Box 2)
    Bound volume. Handwritten with typed title page which reads Hartford, Connecticut State Library, 1927. Some pages are blank or were torn out; these are not listed.
    - Pages 2-3
      A list of implements of Indian manufacture that have been found in Portland, Conn. and vicinity.
    - Page 5: Indian Localities about Portland, Conn.
      Indian Hill, large settlement, noted for Indian relics, on the northwest side of the hill facing the Connecticut River, eastern side of the hill was used as a cemetery.
    - Page 6
      Indian Relics are found along the Connecticut River shore from Indian Hill down to a short distance below Worthingtons where a large elm tree stands. Indian relics are found all along the Connecticut River Bank from Indian Hill up through Wougock Meadow to Tayoutown.
    - Page 7
      There was once an Indian Settlement on the farm of George Palmer near the St. John Chapel. Several Indian relics have been found on the John Shepherd Farm. A few Indian relics have been found on a plowed lot belonging to Hudson Hale on the west side of the meadows opposite Palmer's knoll.
    - Page 8